מנחות מ"ב ע"א Menachot mem-beta amud-aleph and
we’re in the middle of the דף daf and רב אחא בר
יעקב, Rav Acha bar Yaakov, it’s about two-thirds down the narrow lines
right after the vertical square brackets running down the left-hand column. רב
אחא בר יעקב רמי ארבע ואיץ להו מיאץ. Rav Acha bar Yaakov
rami arba ve-ayitz lehu mi-yayitz. So he put four strands of ציצית
tzitzit in his ציצית sissis and he presumably this means folded them
over. This is the most explicit גמרא Gemara that you put the
strings in the hole and you double them over. ואיץ להו מיאץ
ve-ayitz lehu mi-yayitz and he you know folded them over. ומיילו בגלימיה
u-meilo biglimei
and he put it in his in his garment ועביד להו מיבק
va-avid lehu mivak and he knotted it. Now it sounds like he
folded it before he put it in. The you know it’s hard
to know exactly what it means, but it sounds like it’s saying
that he basically looped it, put the loop, the you know the
folded over end through the hole, and then took the string end
and you know and put it through the loop that had gone
through the hole if you can imagine that. It’s like, you know,
it’s a basically it would sort of make a knot automatically. You
know you’d have the loop coming out of the hole and you
take the loop and then you put it through that loop, the
you know and then you would have you would have a knot.
So that’s very different than the way we make it. We put
the open end through then it folds over then we take a
loose string and we make a knot. Anyway that’s what he would
do. ועביד להו מיבק. va-avid lehu mivak. קסבר בעינן תמניא דגלימי. Kasavar
ba’inan tamnaya deglimei. He
is of the opinion that you
require eight in your garment, so you have four doubled over, היכי
דלהוי גדיל גדילים במקום פתיל. heichi delihavei gedil gedilim bimkom petil. So
they are גדיל גדילים gedil gedilim which is the you know presumably
where we learn the idea four from. גדיל gedil is two, גדילים
gedilim is four, במקום פתיל bimkom petil while it is still a
loose string. So it’s four loose string, it becomes eight when it
is doubled over. And now the גמרא Gemara is about to actually
shift and get onto a whole discussion about women’s obligation in ציצית
tzitzit and a very fascinating important discussion about the nature of the
מצווה. mitzvah. So before we leave that I just wanted to say
one final thing here because this is the last of a number
of גמרות Gemarot that you saw yesterday where about the question of
what do you call it about how exact the number of strings
and how you make the knots and so on where you know
where the גמרא Gemara seems like it has a wide range of
possibilities of how you can make it. You know there was an
idea of three strings, four strings, you know all these different שיעורים
shiurim without even quoting פסוקים psukim which is quite fascinating. And this
leads to you know a very reasonable position of the רמב"ם Rambam
which you might be shocked to hear which the רמב"ם Rambam basically
says there’s really no specific number of strings according to the תורה.
Torah. According to the תורה Torah the number of strings is not
specific and the exact way you make it is not specific. Basically
the key is is that you have you know loose you have
a certain number of strings whatever they are, you have some wrappings
כריכות, krichot, you have knots and you have the you know open-ended
loose at the end, some type of a fringe. Which really does
reflect the wide range in the גמרא Gemara without quoting פסוקים psukim
and without the גמרא Gemara like strongly saying that the other ways
are פסול. pasul. And it really makes you think, you know, on
the מצווה mitzvah of ציצית tzitzit it means a fringe and actually
gives you like a lot of latitude about what that fringe is.
A fringe is defined by certain things, knots and loose and so
on, but a lot of the other details are very open which
is you know quite unusual by מצווה mitzvah objects that we have
such a wide range but does reflect some of what this גמרא
Gemara seems to say. Of course not everybody agrees to that. You
know a lot understand that no at the end of the day
there’s a very specific amount, maybe it’s the דאורייתא, de-Oraita, but we
actually פסקן pasken a very specific way. And what we did see
yesterday also was oh actually I’m sorry we’re going to see that
more today. What we’re going to see today is also that even
in the exact knottings there’s some range, there are some very specific
ways it has to be made in terms of issues of like
about like whether you spin it לשמה, lishma, whether you dye the
blue לשמה. lishma. So it’s not all free you know sort of
open. But it is worth noting that the רמב"ם Rambam understands that
מן התורה, min ha-Torah, מדרבנן mi-derabbanan it’s still the four doubled over
but מן התורה min ha-Torah there’s a wide range. Okay so with
that being said we’re now going to turn to a very distinct
topic here about the exact nature of the מצווה. mitzvah. So let’s
take a look. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
רב ירמיה מדיפתי רמי Rav Yirmiya mi-Difti rami I’m sorry I just
did that already.
מר בריה דרבינא עבד כדידן. Mar brei de-Ravina avid kedidan. מר בריה
דרבינא Mar brei de-Ravina did like we do, whatever we do was.
רש"י Rashi says it means four that are doubled over to eight.
Fine. רב נחמן אשכחיה לרב אדא בר אהבה. Rav Nachman ashkechei le-Rav
Adda bar Ahava. רב נחמן Rav Nachman found רב אדא בר אהבה
Rav Adda bar Ahava רמי חוטי. rami chutei.
He was putting ציצית sissis in his garments, in his garment וקא
מברך לעשות ציצית. v-ka mevarech la’asot tzitzit. And as he was putting
in he was making the ברכה beracha אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לעשות
ציצית. Asher kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu la’asot tzitzit. אמר ליה. Amar lei. So
he said מאי ציצית שמינא הכא? Mai tzitzit shamina hacha? What ציצית,
sissis, ציצית, sissis, what ברכה, beracha, what’s going on here? Like what
are you doing making a ברכה beracha at this stage? You’re not
wearing it. הכי אמר רב. Hachi amar Rav. This is what רב
Rav said. ציצית אין צריך ברכה. Tzitzit ein tzarich beracha. You don’t
make a ברכה beracha when you make it, you only make a
ברכה. beracha. Making the ברכה bracha אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לעשות ציצית.
asher kidshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu la'asot tzitzit. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he
said, מאי ציצית שמענא הכא, mai tzitzit shamna hacha, ציצית, tzitzit, ציצית,
tzitzit, what ברכה, bracha, what's going on here? Like what are you
doing making a ברכה bracha at this stage? You're not wearing it.
אז אזוי אמר רב, As azoy amar Rav, ציצית... tzitzit... הכי אמר
רב, hachi amar Rav, this is what רב Rav said: ציצית אין
צריך ברכה. tzitzit ein tzarich bracha. You don't make a ברכה bracha
when you make it, you only make a ברכה bracha when you
wear it. And as you might be guessing, we're going... this very
well could tie in to the discussion yesterday about whether the מצוה
mitzvah is on the garment or is on the moment of wearing.
So let's read this a little more and then we'll get back
to that. He says you don't make a ברכה bracha when you
actually make the ציצית, tzitzit, only presumably when you wear it. So
now the גמרא Gemara does like this. כי נח נפשיה דרב הונא,
Ki nach nafshei deRav Huna, when רב הונא Rav Huna died, I'm
not exactly sure how that's relevant other than that maybe that's when
some rabbis were gathered around. אתא רב חסדא למימי דרב אדרב, Ata
Rav Chisda lermei deRav a-Rav, רב חסדא Rav Chisda came up from
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, so meant to and he asks a contradiction
of רב Rav against רב. Rav. ומי אמר רב ציצית אין צריך
ברכה? U-mi amar Rav tzitzit ein tzarich bracha? Is this really true
that רב Rav says you don't make a ברכה bracha when you
make the ציצית, tzitzit, which is how we פסקן? pasken? והאמר רב
יהודה אמר רב, Ve-ha amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, didn't רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda say in the name of רב, Rav, מניין לציצית בעובד
כוכבים שפסולה? Minayin le-tzitzit be-oved kochavim she-pesula?
How do I know that a non-Jew is not allowed to
make the ציצית? tzitzit? שנאמר, She-ne'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, דבר אל
בני ישראל ועשו להם ציצית, daber el Bnei Yisrael ve-asu lahem tzitzit,
speak to the children of Israel and they shall make for themselves
ציצית. tzitzit. בני ישראל יעשו ולא עובדי כוכבים, Bnei Yisrael ya'asu ve-lo
ovdei kochavim,
only בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael makes ציצית tzitzit that are כשר, kosher,
a non-Jew who makes ציצית tzitzit would be invalid. And therefore of
course you should make a ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא Gemara says,
well, what does that have to do with anything? והאי מאי רומיא,
Ve-hai mai rumiya, what's the relevance of this question? What type of
a question or contradiction is this? So אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav
Yosef, so רב יוסף Rav Yosef said, קסבר רב חסדא, kasavar Rav
Chisda, because רב חסדא Rav Chisda is under the opinion who asked
this question: כל מצוה שהכשרה בעובד כוכבים, kol mitzvah she-hechshera be-oved kochavim,
if a non-Jew could be making the מצוה mitzvah object, then בישראל
אין צריך לברך, be-Yisrael ein tzarich levarech, when a Jew does it
you don't make the ברכה. bracha. כל מצוה שפסולה בעובד כוכבים, kol
mitzvah she-pesula be-oved kochavim, however, if a non-Jew cannot make the מצוה
mitzvah object—you know, and you could think of a whole range of
objects, מצוה mitzvah objects that we make: ציצית, tzitzit, תפילין, tefillin, לולב,
lulav, סוכה—if sukkah the non-Jew cannot make a מצוה mitzvah object, it
has to be done by a Jew, בישראל צריך לברך, be-Yisrael tzarich
levarech, then a Jew has to make a ברכה. bracha. Now, what's
the logic for this? One possibility that is said by תוספות, Tosafot,
literal תוספות, Tosafot, דהשתא אין צריך לברך אסמכתא דצונו ולא לאחרים. d'hashtsa
ein tzarich levarech asmachat d'tzivanu ve-lo l'acherim. That it's like a... it's
a text problem. You know, it's the נוסח הברכה nusach ha-bracha problem.
That really you should make a ברכה bracha whenever you make an
object of a מצוה, mitzvah, but there's a little problem: you can't
say 'who commanded us' to make this if a non-Jew could also
in theory make it. So if a non-Jew can make it, it
wouldn't be relevant to say a ברכה. bracha. That's a little problematic.
Number one, it doesn't explain why you're making a ברכה bracha now,
you're not doing the מצוה, mitzvah, you're just preparing the object. And
number two, it still is true that God has commanded us to
do it, the non-Jew might be able to make it but isn't
commanded. So תוספות's Tosafot explanation is really not satisfying. It seems that
the deeper explanation here is to what degree do you consider, you
know, the making of the מצוה mitzvah object part of the מצוה
mitzvah act. And this came up the other day where we discussed
the נצי"ב's Netziv general approach to, you know, הכשרי מצוה hechsherai mitzvah
that are written in the תורה. Torah. That very often when the
תורה Torah speaks about making the מצוה mitzvah object, it actually tells
you to make the מצוה mitzvah object. And there's almost no better
example than ציצית. tzitzit. It says all the פסוקים psukim are about
making the ציצית. tzitzit. ועשו להם ציצית, ve-asu lahem tzitzit, you know,
'you shall make'. גדילים תעשה לך. gdilim ta'aseh lach. By סוכה sukkah
it's more like a דרשה: drasha: חג הסכות תעשה לך, chag ha-sukkot
ta'aseh lach, and so on. But by ציצית tzitzit ממש, mamash, it's
really a פסוק. pasuk. So the question is how much is the
act of making the מצוה mitzvah object a מצוה mitzvah act itself?
And one of the ways that classically in הלכה halacha you determine
how much does the תורה Torah care about the act or does
it care about the end result is whether it gives criteria in
terms of how it's made, how the act takes place. If you
can do the act anyway—like it's פסח Pesach now, so let's give
an example, this is a famous example that רב חיים Rav Chaim
gives... I won't give you the whole all the all the Torah,
but the basic point is there's a מחלוקת machlokes whether you can
burn חמץ chametz only with fire ערב פסח Erev Pesach or you
can get rid of it in any way. So if you can
get rid of it in any way, we really just care about
the end result, that you don't have חמץ chametz when פסח Pesach
starts. If, however, you have to do an act of burning it
with fire, then the תורה Torah says that there's a specific מצוה
mitzvah act called burning that has to be done here. And that's
why we're defining exactly how it be done. That seems to be
the issue. If the תורה Torah is saying not even a non-Jew
can make a מצוה mitzvah object, so in the end of the
day it's saying we really don't care how this מצוה mitzvah object
is made. All we care is that you have the right object
at the end of the day, that you have ציצית tzitzit on
your garment. That if you have the object that's fine. So if
that's true, you're not going to make a ברכה bracha on the
making of the object because there's no significance to the process. The
only thing we care about is the end result. However, if the
תורה Torah gives criteria in terms of how to make it, that
it has to be done by a Jew, maybe even other criteria
as we're going to see in a minute—it has to be spun
לשמה, lishma, dyed לשמה... lishma... non-Jew might only be one example of
the
criteria—then the תורה Torah cares about the process of making it, and
then you can make a ברכה bracha because then that process is
a מצוה mitzvah act. Might not be a מצוה mitzvah per se,
the real מצוה mitzvah might be wearing it, but at least it
is a מצוה mitzvah act. That seems to be the issue here
about whether a Jew can do it or whether a non-Jew can
do it. And therefore saying, since רב Rav says that a non-Jew
is not allowed to make ציצית, tzitzis, why would he say that
you wouldn't make a ברכה? bracha? That would be a perfect reason
to be making a ברכה. bracha. Okay, so let's take a look
at how the גמרא Gemara continues with this. Obviously this also might
be dependent on whether it's a חובת גברא chovat gavra or חובת
מנא chovat mana or חובת טלית, chovat tallis, which we'll get back
to, but let's for now bracket that for a sec. So let's
see as the גמרא Gemara continues. So the גמרא Gemara says,
וכי כללא הוא, ve-che-klala hu, two lines down in the wide lines,
is this really a general principle?
דב, Dov, you said I skipped רב ירמיה. Reb Yirmiya. Where did
I skip
רב ירמיה?
Reb
Yirmiya?
דב? Dov? Speak up, I'm not facing the computer. Okay, so I'll
check it only periodically. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this:
וכי כללא הוא, ve-che-klala hu, is this really a principle that whether
a non-Jew can do it or not determines whether we make a
ברכה? bracha? והרי מילה, v'harei mila, let's take a look at ברית
מילה, bris mila, דכשרה בעובד כוכבים, d'kishera b'akum,
it's kosher with a non-Jew, which is actually debated in the גמרא
Gemara in עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, question how we rule, presumably we
rule it's not kosher, but this גמרא Gemara is assuming that it
is kosher with a non-Jew. דתניא, De-tanya, עיר שאין בה רופא ישראל
ויש בה רופא ארמאי ורופא כותי, ir she-ein ba rofe Yisrael v'yesh
ba rofe armai v'rofe kuti,
a city that has no Jewish doctor but has a non-Jewish doctor
and a Samaritan doctor. So actually this
does happen a few times that the גמרא Gemara uses the word
ארמאי, armai, Armenian, to refer to a non-Jew. And this is, I
don't know, it's strange because normally when you have these types of
words they reflect censorship of the text. But anyway, here it does
not seem to be the case. Anyway, you have a non-Jewish doctor
and a Samaritan doctor. So the Samaritan is Jewish
but they, as we're going to see, when they do the ברית
מילה, bris mila, they do it for their עבודה זרה. avoda zara.
This is talking at a period when the Samaritans went really off
the דרך derech and started worshipping עבודה זרה. avoda zara. So you
have to choose which one you're going to use as your
מוהל. mohel. ימול ארמאי ואל ימול כותי דברי רבי מאיר, ya-mo armai
v'al ya-mo kuti divrei Rabbi Meir, that's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
because he doesn't want the person doing the ברית מילה bris mila
to be doing it for the sake of his עבודה זרה. avoda
zara. Now you also have to understand that in the context of
מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avoda Zara, the concern is not just in
terms of who's כשר kosher for ברית מילה, bris mila, but can
you trust a non-Jew with a knife around a Jew? Is there
concern given the context of the Roman occupation and so on, was
there concern that they would use the opportunity to injure Jews? So
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying better a Samaritan should do it.
Whether for health concerns or ברית מילה bris mila concerns. רבי יהודה
אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, and we're assuming
that we're ruling like
רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, כותי ולא ארמאי. kuti v'lo armai. I'm sorry, did
I skip a line? ימול כותי דברי
רבי מאיר,
ya-mo kuti divrei Rabbi
Meir,
oh, ארמאי ואל
ימול כותי,
armai v'al ya-mo
kuti, I'm sorry, I said it the wrong way. Let's do that
again. So ימול ארמאי ואל ימול כותי, ya-mo armai v'al ya-mo kuti,
right. So I said it just the opposite way. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says that the non-Jew should do it and not the כותי.
kuti. Right, I think I said it right but I processed it
wrong. Anyway, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the non-Jew should do it
and not the Samaritan, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, because we
do not want the Samaritan doing it for the sake of עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. So it's okay for the non-Jew to do it.
And he does it for עבודה זרה? avoda zara?
What?
No, non-Jew is just doing it as a doctor, you're hiring him
to do a medical procedure. You know, but the we're not assuming
that they're פרום, frum, you know? They're just non-Jews. The Samaritans, they
really are פרום frum about מילה mila and they do it לשם
עבודה זרה. l'shem avoda zara. So he says better a non-Jew should
do it. And רבי יהודה אומר כותי ולא ארמאי, Rabbi Yehuda omer
kuti v'lo armai, better a Jew should do it, a Samaritan even
if he might do it לשם עבודה זרה. l'shem avoda zara. So
we're assuming that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position here is the is
the פסק paskened one, or that even in principle רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda wouldn't even argue with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, there's a question
here of precedent. So you see here that a non-Jew can do
the
ברית מילה, bris mila, וישראל צריך לברך, v'Yisrael tzarich l'varech, and we
know you make a ברכה bracha when you do the ברית מילה.
bris mila. דאמר מר, d'amar mar, we taught, המל אומר ברוך אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על המילה, hamal omer Baruch Asher Kiddeshanu B'Mitzvosav V'Tzivanu
Al Ha-Mila, that you make the ברכה bracha על המילה al ha-mila
when you do the ברית מילה. bris mila. So the גמרא Gemara
says, one minute, so you see, a non-Jew can do it and
you still make a ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא Gemara says, מידי
הוא טעמא אלא לרב? mi di hu taima ela l'Rav?
One minute, you're asking here according to רב. Rav. רב, Rav, נפסל
פוסל, nifsal pasul, רב Rav would say that a non-Jew would be
invalid for the ברית מילה. bris mila. דאתמר, d'itmar, it was taught,
מניין למילה בעובדי כוכבים שפסולה? minayin l'mila b'ovede kochavim she-psula? How do
you know, opposite to what we just taught, how do you know
that מילה mila is not כשר kosher done by a non-Jew? סדר
בר פפא בשמיה דרב אמר, S'dar bar Pappa bi-shmei d'Rav amar, סדר
בר פפא S'dar bar Pappa says in the name of רב, Rav,
again in the name of רב, Rav, ואתה את בריתי תשמור, v'ata
es brisi tishmor,
you observe my covenant. You, presumably, who are in the covenant, observe
the covenant and do the ברית מילה. bris mila. רבי יוחנן אמר
המול
ימול, Rabbi Yochanan amar himol yimmol, the one with, so you shall
surely do the ברית מילה, bris mila, but the double language is
telling you המול ימול, hamol yimmol, only one with a מילה mila
or is commanded in a מילה, mila, not necessarily excluding women, that's
a discussion in the גמרא Gemara in עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, but
anyway only one commanded in the מצוה mitzvah of מילה, mila, the
people commanded, they're the one that can do the ברית מילה. bris
mila. So according to רב Rav it actually works out very nicely
because here you have somebody that is if it cannot be done
by a non-Jew and we do make a ברכה, bracha, so it
remains consistent and we're back to our question about ציצית, tzitzis, if
it cannot if it's not done by a non-Jew then why should
you not be making a ברכה? bracha? Now I want to point
out a couple things. One thing is is that there's an obvious
reason why there's more of an of an of an issue of
making a ברכה bracha by ברית מילה. bris mila. Even if you
say it can't be done by non-Jews the question is still do
you focus on this as a מצוה mitzvah act? We see that
we care more about the process, but are we actually going to
call it a מצוה mitzvah act? Clearly by ברית מילה bris mila
we're going to call it a מצוה mitzvah act and make a
ברכה. bracha. So that makes sense, it doesn't necessarily make sense
require us to say that when it comes to ציצית tzitzis that
we're going to make a ברכה bracha even if even if, that's
point number one. Point number two I should say is that some
scholars indicate, particularly
this what's his name Cohen, why can't I think of his first
name, on the book on this book about ברית מילה bris mila
that he did, which I'm also not remembering the name, it's something
like why are I think it's why aren't Jewish women
circumcised, and I'm trying to remember the first name. Anyway he basically
wants to argue and I think very convincingly that if you look
at the the chronology of the opinions around ברית מילה bris mila
you will notice that the idea of a ברכה bracha gets introduced
later in the תנאי Tannaic period and or and the idea of
a ברכה bracha only gets introduced at the same time where you
start getting criteria like does it have to be לשמה lishma or
the doing it לשם עבודה זרה leshem avoda zara problem. Is a
non-Jew good or not good? So you know his understanding is exactly
that they are dependent תליא בהדדי, talya bahadadi, that exactly this, that
you know at the early opinions that allowed a non-Jew would have
totally not required a ברכה bracha and would have said the goal
is not the act of the מילה mila but getting the end
result. But then a later stage came in and where it was
understood that no, the process is important too, you maybe need לשמה,
lishma, you maybe need a Jew, and then when the process became
important that's also when you start making a ברכה. bracha. And that
there's a תוספות ריד Tosfos Rid that says something very similar. So
within ברית מילה bris mila this is exactly the question within ברית
מילה, bris mila, how much is it producing the result and how
much is it a very specific defined process with criteria and with
a ברכה. bracha. So that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying, by
ברית מילה bris mila it works at least according to רב, Rav,
non-Jew cannot do it and you make a ברכה. bracha. Now we
get back to ציצית, tzitzis, why do you have a problem says
says רב חסדא Rav Chisda making a ברכה? bracha? Since רב Rav
says a non-Jew cannot do it then it should be okay appropriate
to make a ברכה. bracha. So let's keep on looking. The גמרא's
Gemara going to finish developing this idea. This is a great גמרא
Gemara in terms of
conceptualizing this issue about the act of making the מצוה mitzvah object
and to what degree are they מצוות mitzvos or not and how
do you determine if the תורה Torah הלכה halacha cares about the
process or about the end result. So let's see now what the
גמרא Gemara said. הגמרא Gemara says like this, סוכה מסייעא ליה, Sukkah
mesaye'a lei,
so סוכה Sukkah supports this idea of the question of ברכה bracha
being only when a non-Jew cannot do it. תפילין הוי תיובתא, Tefillin
havei tiyuvta, but תפילין tefillin is a contradiction. Let's take a look.
הרי סוכה דכשרה בנכרי,
Harey
sukkah
de-kshira be-nochri, a סוכה Sukkah can be made by a non-Jew. דתניא,
De-tanya, סוכת עובדי כוכבים, Sukkas ovdei kochavim, סוכת נשים, Sukkas nashim, סוכת
בהמה, Sukkas behema, סוכת כותים, Sukkas kutim, סוכה מכל מקום כשירה. Sukkah
mi-kol makom kshira. No matter how a סוכה Sukkah is made basically
you can use for your מצוה mitzvah of סוכה Sukkah any type
of a structure that was made for the sake of providing shade.
As long as it's called some type of a סוכה sukkah which
is looking to the English word here, but some type of a
of a shade structure and that's why it was made, it does
not have to be made for the sake of the מצוה. mitzvah.
Not only does it not have to be made for the sake
of the מצוה, mitzvah, it doesn't matter who made it, even somebody
completely irrelevant to the מצוה. mitzvah. So again notice the interrelationship of
we don't care about כוונה kavana and we don't care about who
did it, so it's not about the process, it's about the end
result. So what type of a סוכה Sukkah can you use? One
made by a non-Jew, one made by women who are not obligated,
one made by a בהמה behema but for animals even if it's
not made for human shade, one made by Samaritans, no matter what
it was made for as long as it's made to provide shade
and no matter who made it it's okay. So we care about
the object, not about the process. Now what's the story about the
ברכה? bracha? And we know מכל מקום כשירה, mi-kol makom kshira, however
it's made it's כשר, kosher, ובלבד שתהא
מסוככת כהלכתה, u-vilvad she-tehei mesukekes ke-hilchasa, as long as it has the
proper amount of shade. Okay but we don't care about the process.
So הגמרא Gemara says ובישראל אין צריך לברך, U-ve-Yisrael ein tzarich le-varech,
and a Jew does not have to make the ברכה bracha when
you're making it. דתניא, De-tanya, העושה סוכה לעצמו, ha-oseh sukkah le-atzmo, if
you're making a סוכה Sukkah for yourself, אומר, omer, you mean you're
not in the business but you're making it because it's your preparation
for חג הסוכות. Chag Ha-Sukkos. You make a שהחיינו shehecheyanu because
according to this, this is a תוספתא, Tosefta, and according to this,
the ברכה bracha of שהחיינו shehecheyanu can really be made for the
חג, chag, for the מצות החג, mitzvat hachag, when you start the
preparation of the מצוה, mitzvah, not even when you do the מצוה.
mitzvah. So when you bind your לולב, lulav, you can make a
שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. When you're getting ready on ערב סוכות, Erev Sukkot, in
principle we don't do it, when you make the סוכה sukkah you
can make the שהחיינו. shehecheyanu. So there's actually two שהחיינו'ס shehecheyanus that
we make, as you know, you make a שהחיינו shehecheyanu in קידוש,
Kiddush, which is about the קדושת היום, kedushat hayom, which you only
make when it's actually the יום טוב Yom Tov itself. There's the
שהחיינו shehecheyanu you make about the מצוות היום, mitzvot hayom, about לולב
lulav and סוכה sukkah and שופר, shofar, which according to הלכה halacha
you can make when you start that preparation, when you get into
the process of making it. This is why I'm going to tell
you a secret why you make שהחיינו shehecheyanu on second day יום
טוב Yom Tov for קידוש, Kiddush, but you do not make שהחיינו
shehecheyanu on second day יום טוב, Yom Tov, for example, for the
מצוה. mitzvah. Why is it when we take לולב lulav on second
day יום טוב Yom Tov we don't make a שהחיינו, shehecheyanu, but
when we make קידוש Kiddush on second day יום טוב Yom Tov
we do make a שהחיינו? shehecheyanu? And the answer is, is because
if you buy into the if you pretend ספיקא דיומא, sfeika deyoma,
so maybe yesterday wasn't יום טוב, Yom Tov, the שהחיינו shehecheyanu for
קדושת היום kedushat hayom would be irrelevant, that שהחיינו shehecheyanu only works
when it's actually יום טוב. Yom Tov. So if yesterday wasn't יום
טוב Yom Tov and today is, you have to make a שהחיינו
shehecheyanu now for קידוש. Kiddush. But when it comes to לולב, lulav,
that's not the הלכה, halacha, because even if yesterday wasn't יום טוב
Yom Tov and all I was doing was getting ready for the
מצוה mitzvah of לולב, lulav, I already can make my שהחיינו shehecheyanu
from the moment of getting ready. So even if yesterday wasn't יום
טוב, Yom Tov, I'm not going to make a שהחיינו shehecheyanu again
when I take the לולב lulav today because I already started getting
ready yesterday. So that is the principle that when you start getting
ready for the מצות החג, mitzvot hachag, you can make a שהחיינו.
shehecheyanu. And back to our point, but what does it not say?
What ברכה bracha do you not make on סוכה sukkah when you're
making it? You don't make על עשיית סוכה. al asiyat sukkah. You
make a שהחיינו, shehecheyanu, you do not make a ברכה bracha for
making it, it's just for getting ready for doing the מצוה. mitzvah.
בא לישב, ba leishev, when it comes to sit in the סוכה,
sukkah, בא אומר ba omer ברוך אתה ה' אלהינו מלך העולם אשר
קדשנו במצותיו וצונו לישב בסוכה. Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam asher
kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu leishev basukkah. Okay, so then you actually make the
ברכת המצוה. birkat hamitzvah. So you make a ברכת המצוה, birkat hamitzvah,
you make a שהחיינו, shehecheyanu, ואילו לעשות סוכה לא מברך. ve'ilu la'asot
sukkah lo mevarech. You don't make a ברכה bracha for making the
סוכה. sukkah. That makes perfect sense, completely consistent with this principle that
we don't care how the סוכה sukkah is made, just that it
is made. So since we don't care about the process, you don't
make a ברכה bracha in the making of it. Great, consistent with
this principle. Now תפילין תיהוי תיובתא, tefillin teihvei tiyuvta, but תפילין tefillin
is a contradiction. How is that? דהרי תפילין דפסולות בעובד כוכבים, deharei
tefillin de'psulot be'oved kochavim, תפילין tefillin are פסול pasul if made by
a non-Jew. How do you know this? דתניא רב חנינא בריה דרבא
מפשרוניא, de-tanya Rav Chanina brei de-Rava mi-Pashronya, so now turning to דף
מ"ה ע"ב, daf mem hey amud bet, because because we taught in
the ברייתא: braita: ספר תורה תפילין ומזוזה, sefer Torah, tefillin, u'mezuzah, a
ספר תורה תפילין ומזוזה sefer Torah, tefillin, u'mezuzah שכתבן she-ktavan that were
written by a צדוקי, Tzadoki, actually there is no גרסא girsa to
here is מין, min, by a heretic or somebody that actually is
a wanton violator of הלכה, halacha, we're not going to now describe
exactly what מין min means, כותי, Kuti, עובד כוכבים, oved kochavim, a
non-Jew, עבד אשה וקטן, eved, isha, ve'katan, a slave, a woman, and
a minor. Obviously the difference is that the first examples about the
מין, min, כותי, Kuti, and עובד כוכבים oved kochavim are people that
are basically not Jewish or have sort of been excluded themselves from
the Jewish community. מין min is הלכתית halachit Jewish but excluded himself,
and the כותי Kuti obviously has some type of that marginal status.
עבד אשה וקטן eved, isha, ve'katan are people that are not fully
Jewish and are not excluded though from the community, but that they
are exempt because as we're going to see they're not in the
מצוה mitzvah of תפילין. tefillin. And we connect the מצות תפילין mitzvot
tefillin to the מצוה mitzvah of writing a ספר תורה sefer Torah
or of writing כתבי קודש. kitvei kodesh. So or so a woman,
a slave, and a minor,
yes.
What about מזוזה? mezuzah? Women are in the פרשת מזוזה, parashat mezuzah,
aren't they?
Yeah, but that's not the דרשה. drasha. We'll see the דרשה. drasha.
The דרשה drasha specifically connects וקשרתם וכתבתם. ukshartem uktavtem. Let's take a
look. So מומר mumar or מומר mumar which is similar to מין,
min, anyway פסולין, psulin, all of these are invalid to write ספר
תורה תפילין ומזוזה. sefer Torah, tefillin, u'mezuzah. The abbreviation by the way
סת"ם, STAM, we've been talking about it until now, but that's the
sometimes there are הלכות halachot that are consistent, apply equally to all
of the writings of these objects which involve the writing of כתבי
קודש. kitvei kodesh. So ספר תורה תפילין ומזוזה. sefer Torah, tefillin, u'mezuzah.
So they're all invalid, why? שנאמר וקשרתם וכתבתם: shenemar ukshartem uktavtem: you
shall bind them, the תפילין, tefillin, for a sign, and you shall
write the מזוזה. mezuzah. So כל שישנו בקשירה, kol sheyeshno bikshira, whoever
is obligated in the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין, tefillin, which would exclude
the case of the women, the slave, and the minor, would also
exclude the non-Jew, כותי, Kuti, and the מין min are less clear
why they're considered to be excluded, but presumably it means like if
they're כופר kofer and they deny the מצוה mitzvah as we learned
the other day, actually כותים Kutim reject this as a מצוה mitzvah
of תפילין, tefillin, so they have somehow excluded themselves from it. But
anyway, we're not going to now go into that in detail. But
anybody who is excluded from who is not obligated or has in
some way been excluded from the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין. tefillin. if
you are in the מצוה, mitzvah, יש בכתיבה, yesh b'ketiva, then you
can write the מזוזה mezuzah and presumably all of these objects. כל
שאינו בקשירה, kol she'eno b'k'shira, if you're not in that מצוה, mitzvah,
in the מצוה mitzvah of תפילין, tefillin, אינו בכתיבה, eno b'ketiva, you
cannot write these objects, assuming that what's true about מזוזה mezuzah is
true also about תפילין tefillin and ספר תורה. sefer torah. So here's
a general principle which is explored in גיטין Gittin and elsewhere, we're
not going to- we are not going to focus on this, but
anyway from which- this we learn out that a whole set of
people cannot write סת"ם, STaM, ספר תורה, sefer torah, תפילין, tefillin, and
מזוזה, mezuzah, and so therefore it has to be done by a
Jew and by a male Jew and an adult Jew and so
on. And nevertheless, we don't make a ברכה bracha in the making,
in the manufacturing of ספר תורה, sefer torah, תפילין, tefillin, and מזוזה,
mezuzah, we only make a ברכה bracha in the fulfilling of the
מצוה. mitzvah. And let's take a look.
ובישראל, u'b'yisrael, when the Jew comes and actually writes it, אין צריך
לברך, ein tzarich l'varech, does not make a ברכה bracha in the
manufacturing of a מזוזה mezuzah or תפילין. tefillin. דשלח ליה רבי חייא
בריה דרב הונא משמיה דרבי יוחנן, d'shalach lei Rabbi Chiya brei d'Rav
Huna mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan, because it was sent in the name of
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
meaning sent from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. על תפילין של יד אומר,
al tefillin shel yad omer, when you put on the תפילין של
יד tefillin shel yad you say אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו להניח תפילין.
asher kiddshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu l'haniach tefillin. That's when you put it on.
We said that before, to place תפילין. tefillin. על תפילין של ראש
אומר, al tefillin shel rosh omer, ברוך אשר קדשנו במצותיו וצונו על
מצות תפילין, baruch asher kiddshanu b'mitzvotav v'tzivanu al mitzvat tefillin, on the
מצוה mitzvah of תפילין, tefillin, you don't use an active verb, we
discussed that before. ואיהו, v'ihu, and however when it comes to לעשות
תפילין, la'asot tefillin, לא מברך. lo mivarech. You don't make the ברכה
bracha לעשות תפילין. la'asot tefillin. So therefore you do not make the
ברכה bracha in the manufacturing. So here we've got a problem. You
see, you do not make the ברכה, bracha, but there are instances
where we care about the process and we still don't make the
ברכה. bracha. And therefore what's the big deal? Maybe רב Rav says
that ציצית tzitzis cannot be made by a non-Jew and still you
don't make the ברכה. bracha. Now I would say that, you know,
that certainly makes- first of all, the fact that we don't always
say it does not disprove our basic approach. The approach could still
be that when you don't care about the process it shows we
only care about the end result and certainly you would never make
a ברכה bracha then because it's all about the end result. When
we do care about the process, then it's possible to make a
ברכה. bracha. You don't have to make a ברכה bracha but it's
possible to make a ברכה. bracha. There would be other factors. For
example, by ציצית tzitzis the תורה Torah says ועשו להם ציצית. v'asu
lahem tzitzit. So by ציצית tzitzis of all things we would make
a ברכה, bracha, we would want to make it by ציצית. tzitzis.
You know, however it is true by מזוזה mezuzah it also says
וכתבתם, u'chtavtam, but there it says וכתבתם על מזוזות. u'chtavtam al mezuzot.
So the כתיבה ketiva is not just writing on the קלף klaf
it's writing on the מזוזה. mezuzah. So yet there we care about
process but we're not necessarily going to make a ברכה. bracha. We
might need another indication beyond that the process matters that this is
considered a מצוה mitzvah process in order to make a ברכה. bracha.
That's point number one. Point number two I would also say is
that the fact that we're
invalidating these people from the writing of סת"ם, STaM, ספר תורה, sefer
torah, תפילין, tefillin, and מזוזה, mezuzah, presumably shows that the problem here
is not in the creating the חפצא של מצוה. cheftza shel mitzvah.
The מצוה mitzvah object- I mean a ספר תורה sefer torah is
not really a מצוה mitzvah object, it's creating the כתבי הקודש. kitvei
hakodesh. What constitutes כתבי הקודש? kitvei hakodesh? It could be that that
has certain criteria, what constitutes כתבי הקודש, kitvei hakodesh, and without this
it's not כתבי הקודש. kitvei hakodesh. But to make a ברכה bracha
of אשר קדשנו במצותיו asher kiddshanu b'mitzvotav means not that we're just-
again, it's not because that the process matters, but it matters in
the context of creating a מצוה mitzvah object. And here by כתבי
הקודש kitvei hakodesh it might matter more in the context of creating
כתבי הקודש kitvei hakodesh than it does in creating these as a
מצוה mitzvah object. Be that as it may, the גמרא Gemara is
saying look, you know, your principle might still make sense, but the
point is that there are times where process matters and you don't
make a ברכה, bracha, where it can be done- it cannot be
done by a non-Jew and you still don't make a ברכה. bracha.
So therefore what was the problem that רב חסדא Rav Chisda had?
רב Rav would say you don't make a ברכה bracha in ציצית,
tzitzis, the fact that only a Jew can make it is not
a contradiction. Yet process matters but still you're not going to make
a ברכה. bracha. We don't always make a ברכה. bracha. So therefore
what was רב חסדא's Rav Chisda problem? And now the גמרא Gemara
continues. דוב, Dov,
do you have a question? I see you wrote some questions. You
still have a question? What?
No?
טוב. Tov.
Hello?
Are you guys on? Okay. All right you're good. All right so
we go on. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay so
what's-
so what's the story? Why did רב חסדא Rav Chisda have a
problem that רב Rav says don't make a ברכה? bracha? Who cares
that it can only be made by a Jew? That doesn't mean
you have to make a ברכה. bracha. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא היינו טעמא, ela hainu ta'ama,
here is the way to determine whether you make a ברכה bracha
when you're manufacturing the objects. It's not just whether it's a Jew
or a non-Jew. There's another factor, or this is the factor that's
critical. What's the factor? Here's the factor. כל מצוה דעשייתה גמר מצוה,
kol mitzvah d'asiyata gmar mitzvah,
any מצוה mitzvah that when you're making it you're done, כגון k'gon
for example מילה, mila, okay when you do the מילה mila that's
the מצוה, mitzvah, you're done, אף על גב דכשר בו עובד כוכבים
וישראל צריך לברך. af al gav d'kasher bo akum v'yisrael tzarich l'varech.
We could say that even if a non-Jew could do Even if
we go against the whole logic we just said, it's all about
the end result. Nevertheless, since when you're done you're done, you make
a ברכה bracha if you're doing it, because if a Jew is
doing it, because then you've achieved what your goal was, which was
to produce a child with a ברית מילה. bris milah. And even
if it is about end result and not process, nevertheless you've achieved
the proper end result. You make a ברכה bracha when you're done,
when you're doing an act that means you're finished, then you can
make the ברכה. bracha. Okay, that's דעשייתה גמר מצוה. de'asiyasa gmar mitzvah.
צריך לברך. tzarich levarech. וכל מצוה דעשייתה לאו גמר מצוה. vechol mitzvah
de'asiyasa lav gmar mitzvah.
However,
when the manufacturing is not the end of the process, כגון תפילין,
kegon tefillin, like תפילין, tefillin, because when you make the תפילין tefillin
or write the מזוזה, mezuzah, you're not done. You still have to
wear them. אף על גב דפסולות בעובדי כוכבים, af al gav depasulos
be'ovdei kochavim, even if a non-Jew cannot do it, and process matters.
So even if the process matters, the way I'm translating what it
means a non-Jew can do it. בישראל אינו צריך לברך. bi'Yisrael eino
tzarich levarech. You don't make a ברכה bracha because you're not yet
done. So if you're not yet done, why can you make a
ברכה? bracha? אשר קדשנו במצותיו. asher kideshanu bemitzvosav. You're not doing the
מצוה, mitzvah, you're just manufacturing the object. So if you're just manufacturing
the object, you then you don't make the ברכה. bracha. So here
the גמרא Gemara says a very reasonable thing, which is if you
actually stop and take a step back and think about it of
all the cases we quoted,
ספר תורה, sefer Torah, תפילין, tefillin, מזוזה, mezuzah, ציצית, tzitzis, סוכה, sukkah,
what was the ברית מילה, bris milah, of all of those, there
was only one that we actually make a ברכה. bracha. What's the
one you make a ברכה? bracha? ברית מילה. bris milah. You know
why you make a ברכה bracha by ברית מילה? bris milah? Because
you fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah when you did the ברית מילה. bris
milah. But in all the other cases when you make מצוה mitzvah
objects, if it's just the object you're making and you're not done
yet, you don't make a ברכה bracha when you're just making the
מצוה mitzvah object. So here the גמרא Gemara is saying forget this
issue, can a Jew do it, can a non-Jew not do it.
It's very simple. If you're finished with the מצוה, mitzvah, you make
a ברכה, bracha, even if in theory you could have had a
non-Jew do it for you. Nevertheless, you fulfilled the מצוה, mitzvah, you
make a ברכה. bracha. If you're just making the מצוה mitzvah object,
then you're not done, then you don't make a ברכה. bracha. And
now we understand why רב Rav says you don't make a ברכה
bracha by ציצית, tzitzis, because you're not done yet with the מצוה.
mitzvah. So אלא, ella, so now the גמרא Gemara turns to what
turns to the other question about ציצית. tzitzis. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. אלא בציצית בהא קמיפלגי. ella be'tzitzis be'ha kamipelgi. So
why is it?
What's the question about making the ברכה bracha by ציצית? tzitzis? The
question would be the basic question of ציצית tzitzis that we raised
yesterday. מר סבר חובת טלית ומר סבר חובת גברא. mar savar chovas
tallis u'mar savar chovas gavra. One understands that it's an obligation that's
about the object and the other is on the person. Now as
you learned yesterday, these positions are not as extreme as they sound.
The position, the idea that the מצוה mitzvah is on the person
does not mean that we have an obligation to go out and
buy a ציצית tzitzis garment, buy a four-cornered garment and put ציצית
tzitzis on it. It means that when I am wearing a garment,
I have to ensure that it has ציצית tzitzis on it. That's
what חובת גברא chovas gavra means. When I'm in certain circumstances, then
I must put ציצית tzitzis on it or make sure that the
ציצית tzitzis are on it. But not that I have to put
myself in those circumstances. That's important because again, all the ראשונים Rishonim
say that even though רב קטינא, Rav Ketina, you know, got the
problem with the מלאך malach about what you doing to avoid ציצית,
tzitzis, that's not because since it's a חובת גברא, chovas gavra, it
means that he has an obligation to find those garments and put
them on. What it means is that if you're living in a
culture where your normal garments are four-cornered garments and you're avoiding them,
you're doing תכסיסי, tachsisi, you know, you're doing schemes to get out
of it, then it's sort of like, you know, the person who
says, well, you know, I really would like a sandwich but I'm
not going to eat it because I don't want to have to
make, you know, I don't want to have to בענטש bentch in
the end.
That's where like the circumstances confront you, are right there and you
and you work around them in order to avoid doing a מצוה
mitzvah which is inconvenient. That's where he got a hard time. But
all the ראשונים Rishonim say that nowadays if our standard garments are
not four-cornered garments, there's halachically no problem. We wouldn't even get a
hard time from the מלאך, malach, you know, if we did not
wear four-cornered garments. Nevertheless, they say of course it's a nice thing
to try to find opportunities to do the מצוה. mitzvah. So when
we say that it's a חובת גברא, chovas gavra, we don't mean
you have to seek out four-cornered garments. We just mean if you're
wearing this garment, then you should put on ציצית. tzitzis. So that's
that's not the extreme. However, it's understood if you say חובת מנא,
chovas mana, it means that even if you never wear it, they're
just in your drawer, you have to put ציצית tzitzis on. And
that's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So do you make a
ברכה bracha on the garment? You make a ברכה bracha on putting
the ציצית tzitzis on the garment. But look, if the idea is
that when I'm wearing I have to put on ציצית, tzitzis, then
the basic מצוה mitzvah is done while I'm wearing. And I'm not
going to make a ברכה bracha when I put them on the
garment, because that's just getting it ready for doing the מצוה. mitzvah.
The מצוה mitzvah is when I put it on. However, if the
מצוה mitzvah is to make sure it's on the garment even when
I'm not wearing it, when it's sitting in my drawer, in my
dresser, like כסותא, kesusa, as שמואל Shmuel says, then as soon as
I put it on, I've done the מצוה. mitzvah. So of course
I'm going to make it. It's גמר מצוה. gmar mitzvah. That is
the מצוה. mitzvah. The מצוה mitzvah is not to wear it. The
מצוה mitzvah is that every four-cornered garment I own, I must put
on ציצית, tzitzis, so I'm exactly doing the מצוה. mitzvah. So at
the end of the day what the גמרא Gemara is saying is
quite simple. It's saying look, forget about it. You don't make a
ברכה. bracha. ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah when you're just making מצוה mitzvah
objects. You only make a ברכת המצוה birchas hamitzvah when you're doing
a מצוה. mitzvah. When are you doing a מצוה? mitzvah? ברית מילה,
bris milah, you're doing a מצוה. mitzvah. Making a סוכה, sukkah, making
a לולב, lulav, you're not doing a מצוה, mitzvah, you're making a
מצוה mitzvah object. How about ציצית, tzitzis, are you doing a מצוה
mitzvah or making a מצוה mitzvah object? Well, that depends. If the
מצוה mitzvah is to wear, when you're putting on ציצית tzitzis at
that moment to ensure that the garment has the ציצית, tzitzis, then
right now you're not doing the מצוה, mitzvah, you're just getting it
ready. If however the מצוה mitzvah is to put it on all
the garments that you own, the four-cornered garments, then right now you're
doing the מצוה. mitzvah. And we should admit that the פשט pshat
of the פסוק, posuk, I mean the פסוק posuk itself has this
tension. On the one hand the פסוק posuk says ועשו להם ציצית,
ve'asu lahem tzitzis, גדילים תעשה לך, gedilim ta'aseh lach,
which sounds like the מצוה mitzvah is to put ציצית tzitzis on
my
garments and that's it, then I've done the מצוה. mitzvah. On the
other hand it says והיה לכם לציצית וראיתם אתו, vehaya lachem letzitzis
ur'ishem oso,
they'll be for ציצית tzitzis and you'll see them, which focus on
the moment of wearing. So that tension about is it just putting
it on the garments or having it on when I'm wearing is
already in the פסוק. posuk. Okay, so that's the question about as
we saw yesterday about חובת גברא chovas gavra and חובת מנה. chovas
mana. And here it says that's why if you make a ברכה,
bracha, it's not because you made a מצוה mitzvah object, it's because
the מצוה mitzvah here is to put the ציצית tzitzis on the
garments even before you wear them. One final point that the קרן
אורה Keren Orah points out about this is he also says that
even the position of חובת מנה chovas mana is not an extreme
because there's a תוספתא Tosefta that says exactly that when you wear
the ציצית, tzitzis, you say להתעטף בציצית. lehitatef betzitzis. And presumably nobody
would disagree with this. So he said even the position that says
it's חובת מנה chovas mana would say why do you put it
on, because eventually you'll be wearing it and it's important when you
wear it as well that you wear the garment that has the
ציצית tzitzis on it and that's part of the מצוה mitzvah as
well. But nevertheless, it also puts emphasis on just having it on
the garments even without wearing them and therefore that's enough to be
making the ברכה bracha at this moment. Okay, so that's basically the
debate. Is that clear? To everybody, you do not make it when
it comes to מצוה mitzvah objects per se. That's not when you
make a ברכה. bracha. You make it when the making of the
מצוה mitzvah object is the מצוה. mitzvah. And the examples would be
מילה milah yes and ציצית tzitzis debatable based on
whether it's חובת מנה chovas mana or חובת גברא. chovas gavra. All
right. All right. So now we will move on. That was a
very beautiful conceptual גמרא Gemara in general about how you think about
making מצוה mitzvah objects and about ברכת המצוה. birchas hamitzvah. This was
a really classic גמרא Gemara and it gets quoted all over by
ראשונים Rishonim in terms of understanding like when you make certain ברכות
המצוה. birchos hamitzvah. All right, so now we continue.
Where were we? אמר ליה רב מרדכי לרב אשי. Amar lei Rav
Mordechai leRav Ashi. So Rav Mordechai said to Rav Ashi about twenty
lines down from the top of the page. אתון הכי מתניתו לה,
Atun hachi masnisu lah, that's how you teach it. אנן הכי מתנינן
לה. Anan hachi masninan lah. This is how we teach it in
terms of this question about can a non-Jew make it. אמר רב
יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav. So Rav Yehudah says
in the name of Rav, מניין לציצית בנכרי שהיא כשרה, minayin letzitzis
benachri she-hi kesheira,
how do you know that a non-Jew can make ציצית, tzitzis, that
it is okay for a non-Jew to make
ציצית? tzitzis? שנאמר דבר אל בני ישראל ועשו להם ציצית. shene'emar daber
el bnei Yisrael ve'asu lahem tzitzis. They shall make for them ציצית.
tzitzis. Who's the they? יעשו להם אחרים. ya'asu lahem acheirim. Get other
people to make
ציצית. tzitzis. Right, classic. Jews will be the foreman, we'll get other
people to do the work for us.
Will there be others to make the ציצית tzitzis for us?
Okay. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehudah amar Rav. So
that's the debate of whether non-Jews can make the ציצית tzitzis or
not. So by the way, if non-Jews can make the ציצית, tzitzis,
it again de-emphasizes the process on the making. Goes back to the
point before and that might also more reflect an opinion that it
is חובת גברא chovas gavra and not חובת מנה. chovas mana. Okay,
so now we go on. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav
Yehudah amar Rav. And now we're going to go on to talk
about how much are there criteria in terms of the ציצית tzitzis
object
itself or the same way are there criteria in the process of
making it. So let's take a look. עשאה מן הקוצין ומן הנימין
ומן הגרדין פסולה. Asa'ah min hakoztin umin hanimin umin hagardin pesulah. If
you make ציצית tzitzis from these various things, it's invalid. What are
these various things? Strands and stray strings? So רש''י Rashi says what
it means is is that they are what is left over from
the weaving or sewing process and they're a natural part of the
garment and they were not put on the garment for the sake
of ציצית. tzitzis. So it's פסול posul because it's basically תעשה ולא
מן העשוי. ta'aseh velo min he'asuy. The idea of ציצית tzitzis is
to take separate strands and insert them in the garment, not to
have these strands left over from the weaving process. The רמב''ם Rambam
says what it actually means is an inferior grade of wool. Like
the קוצין, kotzin, like something that was very thorny and was very
had a lot of junk in it and it was some inferior
grade of wool. That there actually is an invalidity of making ציצית
tzitzis from a low-grade wool. Where we get that from I don't
know, but that's how the רמב''ם Rambam understands this. מן הסיסין כשרה.
Min hasisin kesheira. Wait, what? מן הסיסין, Min hasisin, according
to רש''י, Rashi, didn't we have it
yesterday?
Yeah, so yeah we did. It's basically the same idea yesterday. It's
not significantly different than yesterday.
Okay, so מן הסיסין כשרה. Min hasisin kesheira. From סיסין sisin however
it's כשר. kasher. Now it's getting סיסין sisin seems to be some
type of a wool that was. was that was already spun but
maybe it was made by non-Jews as we're going to see in
a minute.
כי אמריתא קמיה דשמואל ki amritah kimei d'Shmuel when I said it
to שמואל, Shmuel,
אמר amar שמואל Shmuel said אף מן הסיסין פסולה, af min hasisin
pesula, even from סיסין sisin is פסול. pasul. Why? בעינן טוויה לשמה.
ba'inan teviah lishmah. You need that the spinning
of the of the of it be made לשמה. lishmah. And when
you buy ציצית tzitzis strings you'll see on the packaging, you know,
it says, you know, it says like, you know,
טוויה לשמה teviah lishmah etc., etc., was spun לשמה. lishmah.
So that's what you need. So again here the question is to
what degree the מצווה mitzvah objects have to be done in particular
ways. Again, notice it is interesting that שמואל Shmuel is the one
that says that ציצית tzitzis is חובת מנא, chovas mana, that it's
about making that it's on the garment and you're even when you're
not wearing it the garment has to have ציצית, tzitzis, and here
he is the one that's adding this criteria that you need לשמה.
lishmah. The more it's about the garment and the more it is
about the act of putting the ציצית tzitzit on is what's important
and that could also lead to greater criteria in the act of
making. Although you know again it's not necessarily
dependent, we פוסקן paskin this way even though we פוסקן paskin חובת
גברא. chovas gavra. And even if fundamentally the act is wearing it,
nevertheless there are criteria of what constitutes legitimate ציצית. tzitzit. Okay so
here this question is inferior wool or או תעשה ולא מן העשוי
o ta'aseh v'lo min he'asuy and now the real question about טוויה
לשמה, teviah lishmah, the spinning of it does it have to be
לשמה. lishmah. כתנאי, Ke-tanai, this is like a debate of תנאים Tannaim
by תפילין. tefillin. ציפן זהב, Tzipan zahav, if you plated your תפילין
tefillin with gold, או שטלה עליהן עור בהמה טמאה, o she-tala aleihen
or behemah teme'ah, or you used for the boxes, rather than gold
you covered them with the skin or leather of a non-kosher animal,
פסולות psulot they're invalid. עור בהמה טהורה כשרות, Or behemah tehorah kisherot,
a kosher animal they're valid ואף על פי שלא עיבדן לשמה, v'af
al pi she-lo ibdan lishmah, even if the leather of the בתים,
batim, not of the קלף, klaf, but of the בתים batim was
not worked was not tanned לשמה, lishmah, right? The עיבוד ibud is
the normal way you turn animal skin into leather and if that
was not done even not for the sake of תפילין. tefillin.
So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel אומר, omer, רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says אף עור בהמה טהורה
פסולות, af or behemah tehorah psulot, even from a kosher animal it's
invalid עד שיעבדן לשמה ad she-ye'abden lishmah until you do עיבוד לשמה.
ibud lishmah. So the גמרא Gemara says let's make this a general
question. When you need מצווה mitzvah objects, do they have to be
made לשמה? lishmah? Now of course, you know, it's not the same
by every הלכה. halacha. We just learned by for example by סוכה
sukkah that a סוכה sukkah does not require לשמה. lishmah. סוכה Sukkah
could be made for animals and it's kosher to use as a
סוכה sukkah object. So it's not going to be a universal rule
and it is interesting that
the גמרא Gemara puts תפילין tefillin and ציצית tzitzis in the same
category—I mean, we tend to do that because you know we wear
them all during דאוונינג, davening, but it's not necessarily clear why we
would assume they have the same הלכות. halachas. Now it is true
we're not talking about תפילין tefillin as כתבי קודש. kitvei kodesh. We're
talking about תפילין tefillin here in terms of the חפצא של מצווה
cheftza shel mitzvah because we're talking about the בתים. batim. So by
the בתים, batim, what matters is it's not a question about the
parchment inside, it's about using it as an appropriate חפצא של מצווה
cheftza shel mitzvah to do the מצווה mitzvah of תפילין. tefillin. And
the גמרא Gemara understands that if there's a לשמה lishmah requirement there,
it should be required by ציצית. tzitzis. Maybe just because it's all
in the same פסוקים, pesukim, but again it's not exactly clear why
the גמרא Gemara assumes it should all be the same rule. So
let's take a look.
Yeah.
Wouldn't you expect there to be a difference
depending on whether the Torah uses the word ועשו ve'asu or והיה
לכם? ve-haya lachem?
Yeah, well that's what I was saying before, that by ציצית tzitzis
in particular, if any place we would have said that the making
of it matters and that you should be able to make a
ברכה, bracha, it should be by ציצית. tzitzis. And you know, maybe
תפילין tefillin you don't, even if it's non-Jewish not good, maybe ציצית—yes,
tzitzis which is part of the argument by the way why we
should say by ציצית tzitzis it's a חובת מנא chovas mana and
not a חובת גברא chovas gavra because the Torah emphasizes "make ציצית
tzitzis on your garment". So it's not about wearing it, it's about
making them. So yes, I fully agree that if anything by ציצית
tzitzis there's more of an indication that there's a מצווה mitzvah in
the process and in the making. Maybe that's also part of the
whole idea of חובת מנא chovas mana and therefore maybe the criteria
are greater and therefore also it should require לשמה, lishmah, absolutely. תוספות
Tosafot says that. If you take a look at תוספות Tosafot כתנאי
ציפן זהב, ke-tanai tzipan zahav, תוספות Tosafot תימא דלמא ציצית שאני, teima
dilma tzitzis shani, maybe ציצית tzitzis are different. בפרק קמא דסוכה דאתי
גדילים תעשה לך be-perek kama de-Sukkah da-atei u-gedilim ta'aseh lecha and לשם
חובך. leshem chovcha. So he bases it on the word לך, lecha,
לשם חובך. leshem chovcha. But I would also agree with you that
it's, you know, it's about the fact that the Torah specifically emphasizes
the making. Now it does say by the תפילין tefillin it says
וקשרתם, u-kshartem, והיו, ve-hayu, it's more about the act and not about
the making itself. I completely agree, and תוספות Tosafot essentially raises the
same question. Okay, so let's take a look.
Yeah. What about סוכה sukkah then? What about סוכה sukkah though? חג
הסוכות תעשה לך. Chag ha-sukkot ta'aseh lecha.
Yeah, but again, that's more of a דרשה. drasha. Okay, this is
real the פסוקים. psukim. The real פסוקים, psukim, if you have where
are the פסוקים psukim most clear that it's about making the object?
It's about ציצית tzitzis and maybe about מזוזה mezuzah where it says
וכתבתם. u-chtavtam. But that's וכתבתם על מזוזות ביתך. u-chtavtam al mezuzot beitecha.
So you're not necessarily doing the כתיבה ketivah when you're writing on
a קלף klaf on a... your table. But by ציצית, tzitzis, that's
really the most... You're right. Through the lens of חז"ל, Chazal, it's
not specific
to ציצית, tzitzis, but through the פשט פסוקים, pshat psukim, ציצית tzitzis
is why by ציצית tzitzis you have the opinion that it's חובת
מנא chovas mana that you're done when you put the ציצית tzitzis
on on the בגד beged even when without wearing it. So yes,
I do agree that that there's greater there's a logic why it's
more demanded by ציצית. tzitzis. Let's take a look back in the
גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara does like this. Okay, so אמר
ליה אביי לרב שמואל בר רב יהודה. amar lei Abaye leRav Shmuel
bar Rav Yehuda. So אביי Abaye so that's it, there's a debate
about the טוויה, teviyah, about the spinning of the strings. Now there's
another thing that we have to worry about about the making of
the object. So what do we have? Actually if you think about
it we're now going through about the process of making it. So
how do you get the strings? You spin them. Do they need
to be first of all can they be lower grade wool according
to the רמב"ם Rambam no. Do they have to be spun לשמה?
lishma? That's the debate. Now we're now the
earlier
question we asked which should be clear was not about the spinning
of the strings. The earlier question about whether a non-Jew can make
ציצית tzitzis about ועשו להם ציצית ve'asu lahem tzitzis whether about putting
the strings into the hole and knotting them and spinning them. So
A, do they have to be spun לשמה? lishma? B, can they
be put in the hole and made by a non-Jew? And now
we're going to be talking about whether about the blue and the
תכלת techeiles and does that have specific criteria? So let's take a
look. אמר ליה אביי amar lei Abaye so אביי Abaye says to
רב שמואל בר רב יהודה Rav Shmuel bar Rav Yehuda הא תכילתא
היכי צבעיתו לה? ha tcheilta heichi tzavishtu lah? תכלת techeiles how do
you dye your תכלת? techeiles? So אמר ליה amar lei he said
to him משחינן דם חלזון mashcheinan dam chilazon we take the blood
of the
חלזון chilazon וסמנין vesamanin and whatever and certain types of you know
of ingredients. What are סמנין? samanin? Like
whatever, not spices, wouldn't say סמנין. samanin. What is that that you
add to chemical compounds? Anyway, some other type of additives שרמינן להו
ביורא shraminan lehu beyora and we put it into a you know
a what a vat that's boiling a boiling
vat ומרתחינן ליה umartachinan lei we heat up the vat ושקלינא פורתא
בביעתא v'shaklina purta bevita
we take a little bit of the dye with an eggshell as
to take like to draw a sample וטעמינא להו v'taamina lehu
literally means we taste it but what it really means is we
test it. We test to see if it has gotten to the
degree the right degree of blueness if the dye has you know
is where we need it to be and if it's absorbed well
into the cloth. So we take a little bit in this egg,
we dip a little piece of cloth into it and we see
if the dye is ready or not. Okay. וטעמינא
להו באודרא v'taamina lehu be'udra אודרא udra is a sample cloth, we
test it. ושדינא ליה לההוא ביעתא v'shadina lei le'hahu beita then we
throw out that egg with the little amount of dye in it
וקלמינא ליה לאודרא v'kalmina lei le'udra and we burn the cloth sample.
So now of course the question here is since we didn't get
too many details about what ingredients you actually use which is too
bad for the modern day attempts to recreate you know rediscover and
recreate the process of making the תכלת techeiles but what we did
get was a lot of emphasis about the not direct you know
about how you make the sample, how you test it. That you
don't directly dip the cloth into the vat, you remove a sample
and then what you have to dispose of the sample cloth and
the sample liquid. So why is this? So let's see what the
גמרא Gemara says. שמע מינה shma mina from this we can infer
תלת tlat three הלכות. halachos. שמע מינה טעימה פסולה shma mina t'ima
psula we hear that testing invalidates, meaning the reason that we had
to that you know the reason we throw out the the
well let's take it this way. The reason we remove the sample
with the eggshell rather than directly test in the vat itself is
that somehow were we to test in the vat itself we would
invalidate the whole vat. So the testing invalidates. Why we'll see in
a minute but for now we'll leave it at that. Therefore you
want to remove a little bit from the eggshell so you would
not invalidate the whole vat. ושמע מינה דבעינן טוויה לשמה ushma mina
d'beinan teviyah lishma and we also hear that you require טוויה לשמה
teviyah lishma which is why do we have to throw out the
sample cloth?
Why don't we use the sample cloth for ציצית tzitzis as well?
So presumably because the sample cloth was done for the sake of
testing, not for the sake of making תכלת techeiles and therefore it's
not לשמה lishma and therefore it's invalid and that's relevant to our
broader question about לשמה. lishma. Now we're finding that not only do
you need to spin the strings לשמה lishma but if you're making
תכלת techeiles you need to dye them לשמה. lishma. ושמע מינה ushma
mina and we also hear
טעימה
פסלה t'ima pasla that now that sounds like טעימה פסולה, t'ima psula,
טעימה פסלה t'ima pasla means that after you've tested it, why didn't
you take the remnant of the dye after it's been tested in
the eggshell and spill it back into the vat? And the answer
is is that once it's that dye is invalid, it will also
invalidate the rest of the dye if it gets spilled back into
the vat. If you remember the... This is one of the reasons
the גמרא Gemara says that we can't, you know, we're afraid about
wearing שעטנז shatnez in your ציצית tzitzis is because people won't have
genuine תכלת techeiles and we can't trust them to test it and
even as they do test it they'll throw it back in the
vat and then it'll invalidate the whole vat. Okay, so let's read
a little bit more of the גמרא Gemara and then I'm going
to go back and explain a little bit about the idea of
testing and invalidating. So the גמרא Gemara does like this. So the
גמרא Gemara says ושמע מינה תלת. u'shema mina tlat. So the גמרא
Gemara says היינו טעימא פסולה היינו צביעה לשמה. hainu teima psula hainu
tzevia lishma. So one minute, the גמרא Gemara says why is testing
invalid when it's the thing that you tested why is it invalid?
It's because, meaning why does the cloth become invalid? It's because it
wasn't done לשמה, lishma, it was dyed שלא לשמה. shelo lishma. That's
not two reasons, that's one reason. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
רב אשי מה טעמא קמא. amar Rav Ashi ma tama kama. You're
right, it's really say what's the reason? מה טעמא, ma tama, טעימא
פסולה, teima psula, why is something that was tested, cloth that was
used in testing, why is that invalid?
משום דבעינן צביעה לשמה mishum d'beinan tzevia lishma because you need that
it be dyed לשמה. lishma. Okay, now I should say a couple
things about this. Number one, so the גמרא Gemara says it's really
not three things, it's really two, which is no big deal, but
you know very oft the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה תלת. shema
mina tlat. The גמרא Gemara very much likes threes. If you speak
to any speaking coaches, whatever, they'll tell you that people think in
threes. So when you want to say something you always say there
are three reasons. So if there're four make them into three, and
if there're two make them into three, there's always gotta be three
reasons for something. So the גמרא Gemara says שמע מינה תלת shema
mina tlat
that the גמרא Gemara always says we learned three things from this,
even though sometimes it really seems like it's only two things, and
there's a couple of examples where the ראשונים Rishonim are really struggle
to understand why it's three because it really sounded like it was
just two that the גמרא Gemara just called it three. Well here
the גמרא Gemara says that explicitly. Yes we said three but at
the end of the day it really is two, we're just finding
a way to call it three. Okay that's just interesting point number
one, not directly relevant for us. But anyway, more relevant for us
is the issue about invalidating.
Why does it invalidate the string? That we understand, you need it
to be לשמה. lishma. So we understand that and the גמרא Gemara
says that's all one thing. Why the cloth is invalid is because
it wasn't done לשמה lishma and therefore it can't be used. But
that really doesn't get to the point about why the remnant of
the dye is invalid and why it would invalidate the vat if
you were to pour it back in.
Presumably, and we'll just have this for now for our working explanation
and I'll modify it in a minute, presumably since it was used
in creating invalid ציצית, tzitzis, it was used in creating this cloth
that cannot be used as ציצית tzitzis because it was לא לשמה,
lo lishma, so therefore it somehow becomes invalid as well because it
was used in creating this invalid ציצית, tzitzis, and therefore the remnant
of the dye is not good and therefore you need to use
it in a sample, you don't want to dip it in the
whole vat, and therefore even if you threw it into the vat
somehow that would invalidate the rest of the vat. Okay that seems
to be the issue of the גמרא, Gemara, we will clarify that
in the next few lines. So let's take a look. Here are
the next lines of the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay כתנאי. ke-tannai. This is ב' תנאי. beit of tannai'im. טעימא פסולה
teima psula משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar testing the dye is invalid because
it says כליל תכלת kelil techeiles all blue, דברי רבי חנינא בן
גמליאל. divrei Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel. That's what Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel
said. What does that prove anything? We'll see in a minute.
רבי יוחנן בן דהבאי אומר Rabbi Yochanan ben Dahavai omer says אפילו
מראה שני שבכשר afilu mareh sheni shebakasher even if it is the
derivative or the second color it's kosher משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar ושני
תולעת. u-shni tolaat. Not by ציצית tzitzis here but by בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehuna or that's actually by the אזוב, ezov, it says a
red string so שני shni is red as שני. sheni. Now what
are they talking about? רש"י Rashi says what they're talking about is
whether this dye was used once or twice. So what he's saying
is כליל תכלת, kelil techeiles, it can only be used the first
time. Any leftover dye is invalid. This is the way רש"י Rashi
reads it. Any leftover dye is invalid. So therefore when he's saying
the second thing he's saying no no I could have used it
once for one thing and then leftover dye I'll use now to
make my my שני תולעת, shni tolaat, to make my תכלת, techeiles,
to make all the same stuff. So for רש"י Rashi it's not
about having been done שלא לשמה, shelo lishma, it's about having been
used the first time or the second time. And that's why we
don't want to test in the vat itself because then the entire
remainder would be stuff that was left over from a single use
from a previous use. תוספות Tosafot says that that's crazy, we've never
heard that you cannot use a huge vat multiple times for making
multiple kosher you know strings of תכלת. techeiles. It's not about using
it once or twice. It's not just about the fact that it
was second use. It's about the fact that the first use was
an invalid use. And since the first use was an invalid use,
therefore this is considered to be left over from an invalid use
and that makes it invalid. That's how תוספות Tosafot explains this.
So if you tested it somewhere in the middle you're okay! What?
So if you tested it somewhere in the middle you're okay.
What do you mean somewhere in the middle?
I started using it for a כשר kosher ציצית tzitzis and then
I said, "You know what? Let me test if this is real"
or not. Oh, no. No, no, no.
No, according to, apparently the way תוספות Tosfos understands it is anything
leftover from an invalid use. The idea of שני sheini means it's
leftover from having been used in a wrong way. So
once whatever the quantity is, whether it's the vat or the eggshell,
was used in a wrong way, it makes all the rest invalid.
That's the way תוספות Tosfos reads it. But again that's not so
clear in the language of כליל kalil or שני. sheini. The best
read of this comes from the קרן אורה Keren Ora who's an
אחרון, achron, one of the few אחרונים achronim on מנחות, Menachos, and
he says it's brilliant. He says the issue here is whether the
dye that requires testing is a reflection of how good of a
dye it is. If it is a really excellent quality dye you
don't have to test it like you know that it's excellent, you
know it's תכלת, techeiles, you wouldn't bother testing it. As soon as
you've tested it you've shown that you're
questioning the quality of the dye. So then it's not like כליל
תכלת, kalil techeiles, then it's like what the גמרא Gemara says מראה
שני. mareh sheini. שני sheini is like second grade, it's like,
so therefore that's the question. Dye that needed testing is the way
he reads it. So it's a little trick then. If you take
it in an eggshell you're not testing the dye in the vat,
you're only testing the dye in the eggshell. So then you could
pretend like you've never tested the dye in the vat. But the
way he reads it has nothing to do with שלא לשמה. shelo
lishmah. It has to do with the fact that if I made
this into dye that required to be tested then I've invalidated it.
That is the first way. Then with זו היא מראה שני zu
hi mareh sheini even if you showed that it needed to be
tested you haven't invalidated it. I thought that was a very lovely
read of this. The other thing of course to point out is
that it's being compared to other things. בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, אגודת
אזוב, agudas eizov, and in particular the comparison to בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna is I think a subtext that's been running through a lot
of this. I don't know if Dov mentioned it yesterday but the
whole issue about
wearing כלאים kilayim in your ציצית tzitzis even when it's not for
the מצוה, mitzvah, even when it's not necessary, תוספות Tosfos says that
he has a whole רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam approach on that that
even if you're wearing your ציצית tzitzis at night or even if
a woman's wearing ציצית tzitzis and you're not really doing the מצוה,
mitzvah, but once it's defined as a garment of ציצית tzitzis there's
no problem of the fact that the ציצית tzitzis turned it into
שעטנז. shaatnez. And he makes comparisons with that to the בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehuna that at least some of the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna
were by definition שעטנז. shaatnez. So that's also interesting, the implicit comparison
here to בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Okay, it's already pretty late, let's
just finish this up to the bottom of the דף. daf. What?
I was
going to
say we need to sign off.
Okay, so then we'll sign off here, but let me ask so
I'll be there in person Friday and שבת Shabbos so what we'll
do is could you just I think we're going to have to
do it twice on שבת Shabbos because we're a full דף daf
behind.
Okay, so before and after מנחה?
Mincha? Yeah. Alright, so to be continued tomorrow everybody. חג שמח, Chag
sameiach, מועדים לשמחה. moadim l'simcha.